Welcome!
In this video, we'll explain how to manage your handling times and fulfillment settings.
There are four main settings that can affect order handling times.
Default handling time, handling capacity, weekend operations, and asin-specific handling time.
Each of these can make a big difference when it comes to making a sale.
Why is handling time so important?
It's a key part of earning customer trust.
Every offer in the Amazon store comes with a customer delivery promise.
This is the range of dates in which a customer can expect an order to arrive.
The customer delivery promise consists of handling time, which is the number of days needed for
you to prepare and ship orders.
Transit time, which is the number of days your selected carrier needs to deliver packages.
And occasionally, additional buffers to protect your delivery promise in case of carrier delivery
issues or weather events.
It's important that customers receive their orders before the final date of the customer delivery
promise.
Products that arrive late make customers doubt if you can deliver on time.
Late deliveries can also hurt your account health.
If a customer sees two offers in the Amazon store that are the same price but have different customer
delivery promises,
the offer with the shortest customer delivery promise will be more likely to win the featured offer.
Since that's the one customers will be more likely to purchase, it's in your best interest to have
the most accurate handling time possible.
A 2019 study found that merchant fulfilled sellers in the US overestimate domestic handling times
by an average of 53%.
That means that their customer delivery promises are longer than they need to be, which makes for
missed opportunities.
The most basic way to improve your customer delivery promise is to shorten your default handling
time.
Depending on when you created your seller account, your default handling time was set to one or
two days.
A one day handling time means that you'll ship an order by the end of the business day after it
was received.
While a two day handling time adds another business day.
If you can prepare orders quickly, shortening your handling time will make your offers more appealing
to customers.
If you ship your orders out on the same day that you receive them, you may want to switch to same
day default handling time.
Unlike one day handling time, same day handling time means that you'll ship orders on the same day
they're received,
provided the order was placed before a set cutoff time.
Note that same day handling time isn't the same as same day delivery.
Same day delivery is part of premium shipping and means that customers will receive an order on
the same day it's placed.
Same day handling time means that you'll send an order out on the same day that it's placed,
provided that the order was received before a set cutoff time.
The default cutoff time is 2 p.
m.
in your local time zone, but you can edit this to suit your needs.
To change this time, hover over the gear icon in the upper right corner of Seller Central and click
Shipping Settings.
On the Shipping Settings page, under the General Shipping Settings tab, locate the Order Fulfillment
Settings section, then click the Edit button.
On the Order Fulfillment Settings page, scroll down to the Carrier Specific Preferences section
and choose a time from one of the order cutoff time drop down menus.
To set your default handling time, open the Settings menu in Seller Central.
Select Shipping Settings and then choose General Shipping Settings on the next screen.
Scroll down until you find Handling Time.
If you haven't changed anything since creating your account, this will be set to one or two days.
To the right, select Edit.
You'll find an option for same day handling time here.
Select the circle in front of same day under Choose Your Default Handling Time, then select Save.
It may take up to 30 minutes for the new handling time to be reflected in your delivery promise.
Because setting a new default handling time means adjusting the customer delivery promise for all
of your ASINs, you can only change your handling time once every 24 hours.
You may be worried that setting a short handling time could cause a problem if you receive a sudden
spike in orders.
Sometimes you can see spikes coming, like around the holiday season.
Other spikes may be unexpected, like if your brand suddenly becomes popular or a customer places
a large order.
Keeping the customer delivery promise is important, but you don't need to extend your default handling
time to accommodate potential spikes in ordering.
Instead, you can set your order handling capacity.
Order handling capacity sets a limit on the number of orders you can fulfill within your default
handling time.
If you have a one-day default handling time and the number of orders you get exceeds your order
handling capacity, Amazon will automatically add a day to the handling time and set all additional
orders to a two-day handling time.
Note that these orders will count towards your next day's limit.
So, if your order capacity is 100 orders and you get 120, the extra 20 are put toward the next day's
order capacity.
This way, you'll never have more orders than you can handle and you can protect your account health.
You set your order handling capacity in the same place that you set your default handling time.
If you scroll down, you'll see order handling capacity right under default handling time.
Here you set your capacity.
Then select save below.
Note that order handling capacity only affects non-prime orders with handling times between zero
and two days.
If you've set a handling time greater than two days for a specific ASIN, orders for that ASIN won't
count towards your handling capacity.
Weekends and holidays normally count as non-business days in the customer delivery promise.
So, if your handling time is normally two days and someone purchases your product on a Monday, you'll
be expected to ship by Wednesday.
In addition, Saturday and Sunday won't count towards your handling time for a product purchased
on Friday, which you'll be expected to ship on Tuesday.
If you're able to ship products on the weekend, however, you can make your listings more appealing
to customers by enabling weekend operations.
You can do so on the order fulfillment settings page.
Scroll down to account level preferences or select it from the menu on the left to edit your settings
for weekend operations.
Here, you can choose to have your packages picked up by shipping providers on Saturday, Sunday,
or both.
You may have enabled shipping settings automation or SSA using your shipping templates to automatically
calculate your delivery promise.
If so, you'll also need to enable weekend operations for SSA-enabled products in the carrier specific
preferences section, which can be found on the order fulfillment settings page.
Note that you won't set a cutoff time for SSA.
That's calculated automatically.
For more information on SSA, search for shipping settings automation in Seller University or in
Seller Central.
Once you've chosen your desired settings, don't forget to save them using the button in the upper
right.
That covers how to set handling settings that affect your whole catalog, which will help you offer
a better customer delivery promise.
But what if you want to set a short default handling time, but some of the ASINs in your catalog
are hard to get out of the door in one day?
Setting ASIN specific handling times can be the solution.
If you have a product that you can ship out faster than your default time or one that needs more
time than normal, you can use an ASIN specific handling time to give customers more accurate delivery
promises.
As an example, if you've set a same-day default handling time, but one particularly delicate product
needs special prep before it gets shipped out, you could set that ASIN to a two-day handling time
while still delivering your other products swiftly.
Because ASIN specific handling times need to be set separately for each ASIN, you don't set them
from the shipping settings page.
Instead, you'll find these settings on the Manage Inventory page.
To get there, open the main menu in Seller Central by clicking the menu icon in the upper left corner.
Hover over Inventory, then select Manage All Inventory.
Select the checkbox next to the ASIN in your inventory that you want to modify.
Then select the Edit button at the far right end of that row.
Depending on the size of your screen, you may have to scroll to the right to find that button.
On the next page, select the Offer tab and then scroll down to Handling Time.
You can set the handling time here in Business Days, so if you enter two, it means that you'll have
two business days after receiving an order for that ASIN in which to both ship the product and confirm
the shipment in Seller Central.
While you'll normally need to set ASIN specific handling times for ASINs one by one, you can upload
a file to set handling times in bulk if you're familiar with the Inventory Loader tool.
Search for "Modify" handling time in Seller Central to learn more about this option.
Handling time is a key part of the customer delivery promise and your account health, so it's important
to have an accurate handling time for each product you sell.
Remember, having an accurate customer delivery promise is an important part of being a successful
seller.
Customers prefer offers with shorter delivery times, so it's important for your business to have
the best handling time possible.
That begins with setting the right default handling time.
You can set order handling capacity, cutoff time, and weekend operations to improve this setting
while protecting your account health.
For ASINs that require special care, you can set ASIN specific handling times while still keeping
your default handling times for the rest of your catalog.
This can help you delight customers and maximize your performance in the Amazon Store.
This concludes our training on handling times and fulfillment settings.
Thank you.